[Music]
hello everyone welcome to actinflab
livestream number 43.2
it is may 11 2022.
welcome to the actin flap we're a
participatory online lab that is
communicating learning and practicing
apply active inference
you can find us at the links on this
slide
this is a recorded and archived live
stream so please provide us with
feedback so we can improve our work
all backgrounds and perspectives are
welcome and we'll follow good video
etiquette for live streams
if you want to learn more about what's
happening at actinflab
greetings
head over to activeinference.org
and you can find out more about
participating on live streams or
other modes of participation
and today we're in 43.2
where as always it's uh up to the last
minute with what we actually do
and welcome also to stephen
uh we're going to continue this
discussion in our third part
of the
conversations we've been having on this
paper
predictive coding a theoretical and
experimental review
and
we'll begin with the introductions
and then we can
move around the paper we brought up some
things that we'd like to cover
last week
for today but also we can take it any
questions or areas or sections that any
of them want to talk more about we can
absolutely go there so we'll just start
with introductions and say hi and feel
free to
add anything you'd like um
what
brought you to the paper or what's just
one thing that you took away from it and
then i'm sure we'll have some fun today
so i'm daniel and i'm a researcher
in california and i'll pass it to dean
how goes it dean
oh sorry i was muted in jitsi so
it was on the live stream but welcome to
dean and steven
and uh
i'll also share the slides with you here
in the chat but we're
live and in the game so feel free to say
hello
and anything um uh just to
get us going with this discussion
getting a bunch of feedback on
from somewhere daniel
let's go it's going good
i'll i'll open up another window so that
you can see what slides i'm working on
um
but yeah how goes it or what what was
interesting to you about this paper
do you hear me dean
that's me
okay
all right all right
i can hear you now yeah i could hear you
i couldn't hear you before sonic was
weird sound fine dean
i can hear you daniel but there's a long
delay and uh there was a i can hear i
could hear feedback like a second audio
loop going off while you were talking
okay did you have the stream open or
anything
i just
no i just have the picture of the of the
three of us okay i'll just reload just
to be sure
so it goes with live streams
all right
okay so is that better
we'll
roll with it then
so
okay or
we'll see what happens so yeah steven
how goes it and what do you like about
the paper as we start
well i'm just interested in the general
scope
um
as per normal so i'm sort of going to go
with the go with the
the overall vibe of
um
pushing the boundaries of active
imprints
um i'm fairly i'm fairly relaxed with
this one
okay hey dean work better
yeah my my bad
all good all good thank you for telling
me not to have both jitsi and the
youtube open at the same time so
yeah
that uh
these little technical things that i
should have been uh more on top of
there's like some reflex where if your
own audio is played back to you at a
certain delay it makes it like basically
implausible to speak it's pretty
interesting
yeah well apologies guys that's not the
start i wanted
all good so how goes it or what like
brought to you to this paper or what did
you find interesting and what they wrote
well
i'm i'm not really totally up on on what
predictive
coding
is i think i know what predictive
processing is and when when you
and maria were talking in the dot zero
or you were blue or talking in the dot
one
um
just the sort of the translation of that
into
operations that you can
you can
identify with a certain amount of
confidence
is the part that i'm really interested
in i'm not really sure what the
applications are
beyond the psychology realm i'm sure
there are quite a few and that's kind of
why i showed up today was to sort of
piggyback on what what people who
obviously know a lot more about this
than i do
are saying about it and where it's going
and what the potentials of it are
all right well let's
start with a few
reminders and recalls
is there any area or figure or formalism
that either of you would like to suggest
that we jump to to remind ourselves of
anything critical about the paper
otherwise i can
bring this to some
is it okay to start with the back
propagation of error
all right
so i'll bring in this was in um section
four so i'll be bringing in some but
let's um we're gonna ramp into it
just as a reminder about the roadmap
so the first section of the paper is an
introduction
the second section of the paper
describes with quite a lot of detail
the core
kernel of the predictive coding
architecture this is a computational
architecture and it involves information
transmission
that is in this predictive coding way so
check out the paper the zero the dot one
that's where we're going into a lot of
detail on predictive coding as an
information architecture and then as
maria was
bringing out for us predictive
processing might be used to refer
perhaps more holistically to systems
engaging in predictive coding and
there's a bi-directionality there to
predictive processing whereas predictive
coding might be something that could be
done in a bit more of a
uni-directional way
that was section two on predictive
coding
introducing the kernel and then going
into a few specific generalizations of
that kernel and modifications that help
make it more computationally powerful as
well as linking it closer to certain
biological architectures of tissues like
in the retina and in the cortex of the
mammal brain in predictive coding in the
brain three
there's some
exploration on different paradigms of
predictive coding and these are
referring to kind of like settings
where the core and elaborations can be
applied
and that's in the supervised and
unsupervised cases as well as thinking
about spatial and temporal predictive
coding algorithms
and
connections with modern machine learning
like with deep predictive coding
then
after that sort of kernel and
generalization of the predictive coding
kernel
and
exploring some of the paradigms for
where that kernel and its elaborations
have been applied in section four
there's the relationships
between and among their algorithms and
so that's where we get into this section
on predictive coding and the back
propagation of error
so that's where we'll go
and um
i'll copy in some formalisms or find out
um which ones would be the best to bring
in
but um
here we are on slide 56 which i'll share
in the chat here
what is interesting to you about back
propagation of error then we'll start
there
well what i'm curious about is is the
that bottom line of that slide this
recursion is identical to that of the
propaga
to the propagation of air algorithm
which i'm not which i'd never actually
encountered before this
so i was wondering i i know a bit about
recursion i think we all have a sort of
a basic understanding of what's involved
in recursive
um loops but i was wondering
how
sort of the predictive
where's the where is this relationship
between predictive coding and this other
algorithm which i've heard that i've
heard that that i don't know if it's an
expression or label back propagation of
error but i've never really
looked at
at it from a from a operational
standpoint or you know how it's
how it's laid out mathematically and i'm
not sure if either of you have that
familiarity but i was hoping maybe you
did
great so how does predictive coding
relate to the back propagation of error
let's um
look at these sections which we didn't
annotate too heavily leading up to
because you know there's like
many equations in the paper many areas
um
even before we introduce the formalism
and to give me 15 seconds to read it
qualitatively what would back
propagation of error mean to you or
where is an applied setting where you
think this could matter
well
and again this is this is me
talking out loud hanging my butt out
there because i don't really know what
i'm talking about but in my am i correct
in assuming that it's
um
any time you find yourself in feedback
and feed forward loops
i know that they're acyclical
and i know
that usually implies a directional
but isn't anytime you're getting sort of
a a
looping condition where you get an
opportunity to sort of reset
isn't that what we're isn't that the
situation that we're examining
okay
we're in
the arena of
statistical bayesian graphs so we're
talking about models here we're not
necessarily talking about what an actual
system is doing a computer system nor
some sort of biological system we're
talking about a modeling statistical
architecture and it would be a secondary
conversation about what systems are
actually doing with back propagation so
this isn't just like salt water flowing
from the ocean into the river okay just
to sort of force all any preliminary
connections we might want to draw but we
can see when
we have a bit more sense of what back
propagation of error is on this
graphical setting
how it could apply
so they're introducing this concept of a
computational graph fancy g
not free energy related just g for graph
and it consists of two kinds of elements
just like all graphs or networks do
which is vertices and edges
the vertices are representing
intermediate computation products for
example
the activations at each level this
multi-level predictive processing
architecture so we have like nodes
within the level and then there's edges
that represent influence
um
here
as differentiable functions
so this
is related to some of the graphical
bayesian approaches we've looked at
previously but also it shares a lot with
some neural network representations
where the edges are not just like a
correlation or mutual information but
the edges are more like a differentiable
function
we're going to restrict to looking at
specific kind of graphs here
which are computation graphs they're
saying are directed acyclic graphs so
that means that it's directed there's an
arrow
such that the differentiability of the
function is going from one way to the
other like we can think of that as the
forward direction
and then
the
acyclic-ness
is just ensuring that there's like sort
of one place where we could start and we
could just forward propagate everything
out to the edges
and that wouldn't trap us into an
infinite recursion by going forward
and we've talked about some of the
differences between like cyclic and
acyclic graphs with
majeed when we were talking about the
the dcm the
and all the ambiguities of that acronym
um okay
steven anything and then we'll continue
just one quick question um
ontologically how how
useful or problematic
is the word coding now we've moved a bit
further down with active inference
and
in a way is back propagation of error
needed to be that
needs to be distinguished out even in a
descriptive term just so that
the the connotations of coding don't
sort of confuse all the discourse
um what are your innovations
well that it's basically kind of almost
like a representational kind of um
script almost that's been written
somewhere
it's kind of how you know like the
coding that you get in a computer
program or something
um
and i kind of think that
that
does sort of speak to the nature in a
way because it's this is the the nature
of how
um for the future
but um
back propagation of error
um
kind of
speaks in some ways to the nature of how
the code
is processed
um
and i may be off off topic here but i
just i just kind of wonder as we're
going through this and trying to
link it all together
how much
that ontological term
um
is is
also possibly something that could be
thought of in another way make it easier
to to
to to understand what's going on
okay
um
we are dealing here with
computational architectures so i don't
think we need to run away from
these
questions that were brought up more in
a philosophical non-computational
version into the anti-computationalist
perspective like we're not fighting for
what is happening in the brain here
we're using predictive coding to talk
about information coding and
transmission approaches
so that's one thing and um
yeah i mean we don't we can't just go
around flipping different words
predictive coding is what for decades
has been referenced by a certain
architecture here
and then
there's a lot of openness with how that
architecture is applied
but i
i i'm not 100 sure like
this is about predictive coding
architectures
yeah no that's cool i'm i'm just putting
that out there just seeing how that
floats a little bit i think that's a
good good response like what else would
what else could be in this position of
coding
it's about how signals are encoded what
is being transferred between different
nodes
is what is being transferred the raw
value
or
in the predictive coding architecture
we have
um
two directions
that signals are being passed
in this compute graph not in the brain
and that
would be
coming from
um
one direction
the expectation that's the predictive
part and then the error residual
that's the deviation from the
expectation
and so that is what the predictive
coding architecture is
it's just about
having graphical systems
that are passing
expectations and differences or errors
rather than passing like just the plain
values themselves
yeah
i suppose there's also that question of
um
how much is in
the dynamics of what's going on and the
hyper parameters when looked out
and um how much difference that makes
to to the story
okay so you've got you've got the the
the the predictions uh the prediction
error has been passed down
um but coding tends to be like the
numbers are there
but in some ways the numbers can kind of
evolve once the
the system the dynamics of the systems
or the dynamical
sort of
patterns of the system start to
sort of fire up so to speak you know it
takes a little bit of time for the
active influence model to start
really purring along
sometimes
so that kind of coding
is in a way sort of almost more live
than
traditional coding which is kind of sort
of baked in
okay i got you we're not even in active
inference yet so i see some back later
but we're discussing predictive coding
back propagation of error
and then action does get brought into
the picture in section four five
but up until section four or five
there's no action
even in the model so we're just looking
at the architecture that does
computation
and then understanding
how action could be brought in and
that's kind of the fun surprise that we
uncovered in the dot zero and dot one
and in the layout of the paper was when
the architecture is sufficiently general
and powerful
incorporating another variable that is
about action
like policy selection becomes fluent and
that's
why these architectures are composable
with different sensory modalities with
different scopes of action with
different affordances all these things
because there's a level of
generalizability that we can pull back
to
okay so
let's return to predictive coding and
back propagation of error
we have this graph
the vertices are representing
intermediate computational project
products so like a number or like a
variable
because it's kind of like where you're
storing the intermediate computation
product and then the edges
differentiable functions
could be you know like y equals 2x is a
differentiable function anything that
has smoothness in the graph is
differentiable
and as the orange part says we're
restricting this to
directed acyclic graphs where we're not
going to get into an infinite regress
just by going forward
now what happens
when we're trying to
tune
this architecture
so that it has a minimized loss function
loss function whether we're dealing with
least squares error like a regular
linear regression
or whether we're dealing with some other
loss function the loss function is like
what is trying to be minimized
so when the ball is rolling downhill
we're minimizing like the loss or the
energy function but the energy function
approach and wording is coming more from
like a physics
side whereas the loss function is just a
purely statistical claim like what is
the function that we're minimizing
okay
given the output vertex v out
so this is like the one that we actually
want um to be
reducing the loss around
the loss function is going to be l
l is a function of v out
back propagation can be performed upon a
computation graph so we're going to be
minimizing loss
at a certain vertex
by back propagating upstream
a lot of what led to it being the way it
is
and so that could be done on just the
last
tip of the spear or it could be done
throughout the whole system
back propagation is an extremely
straightforward algorithm
which simply uses the chain rule of
multivariable calculus
to recursively compute the derivatives
of children nodes from the derivatives
of their parents
okay so
formalism 28
this fancy d is partial differential
so the change of the loss function
with respect to the change in an
intermediate variable i
is what we're looking at we're looking
at how
we're going on that bowl are we dropping
on the loss function
are we is the model getting better or
worse
with respect to changes of intermediate
computational products vertices
and that
overall loss function
is the sum
of
v
the subset of p which is the parents
so we're looking at v i
like the um node that we're focused on
node of interest or something
and we're going to sum over all of its
parents
and then for all of its parents we're
going to compute something that's
basically like the change in loss
function over the change in that
parent's value v sub j
and how it changes with respect to
change in the child
so we're taking something that's like
this graphical network
with nodes and edges
and differentiability
and then figuring out which way is the
overall downhill
based upon all of the back propagation
of the gradients
okay by starting with this output output
gradient
that's v out
um
and if all the gradients
are known
so like we're dealing with a model that
we specified
then the derivatives of every vertex
with respect to the loss can be
recursively computed so
because all the edges are differentiable
the big function is also differentiable
so like 2x is differentiable x squared
is differentiable x cubed and x to the
11th power are all differentiable
functions
so you could also differentiate
their concatenation through addition
that'd be like the derivative of 2x plus
the derivative of this
and also the chain rule in calculus
allows us to like nest those so if we
can differentiate 2x and if we can
differentiate x squared we could
differentiate
2x
inside of parentheses squared
that's basically the chain rule in
calculus
um and then
that is what allows this sort of
big downhill computation
based upon the specification of the
graph
and then the back propagation of all the
relevant nodes and finding out how those
need to be tuned so that the final
output node that's being
optimized
can be going downhill defined as going
down on the loss function less loss is
better here
okay yes
excellent thank you because this was one
big opaque markov blanket to me when i
read it i just couldn't make any sense
of it but
is the ability to differentiate or what
they is what they're saying here is the
ability to differentiate an ability to
build
relationship that parent-child thing is
is it that is it the capacity to
differentiate that allows
for the relationship to be identified or
is it the other way around because
when when they're talking here
and saying
back propagation performed on the
computation graph
back propagation is extremely
straightforward
and uses the chain rule of multivariate
stuff when it's talking about that it's
it's
it's pointing back to something that you
don't necessarily have to see but you
know that there is some relationship
just like there is between
2x and x squared am i getting
is that is your explanation helping me
move closer to a better understanding of
that
because i understand derivatives but i'm
not sure how the derivatives
fit into this explanation
great
yeah i think we're um
we're
so solenoidally exploring now
we haven't even brought in predictive
these equations here
are for 28 and 29
are about back propagation on
computation graphs
so
with these papers it's really important
to know like what has not been brought
onto this diction
and there isn't error
this is just about the nodes and edges
like the intermediate computation values
of the abstractest kind
and their differentiable relationships
so now they're going to
show how predictive coding relates to
back propagation of error
so they write predictive coding can also
be straightforwardly extended to
arbitrary computation graphs
to do this we simply augment the
standard computation graphs with
additional error units for each vertex
so let's recall what some of these
graphs that we previously looked at here
in figure 1 of the paper
we have a graph
where the nodes are intermediate
computational products
represent differentiable relationships
and importantly some of these
intermediate products
have the semantics or the interpretation
of being estimates about mean mu
at that level or estimates about
variance and error at that level epsilon
so this is kind of like
a subtype of graph like the abstract is
kind it's just intermediate
computational products
and then predictive coding
are specific kinds of computational
graphs
where some of the nodes represent mean
estimates and some of them are error
estimates
in contrast and hopefully not to confuse
here's from 26.2
where we talked about like integrator
chains
so notice that all of these nodes can be
interpreted as intermediate
computational products but there's no
error term here so this is an example of
a computational graph that doesn't have
error terms this is not a predictive
coding architecture not that it's
inconsistent with or somehow disjoint
from but this is not having epsilons so
it's not a predictive coding
architecture whereas this is sort of a
canonical multi-level predictive coding
architecture
okay great
hey jax good to see you
in the chat okay now we're gonna return
back to the back prop
okay
so we're adding in these additional
error units epsilon sub i for each level
of the um graph formally the augmented
graph becomes now g tilde so previously
fancy g was just edges and vertices
nodes and edges and now the vertices is
is being unpacked so that v can remain
for the mean estimators
which are ultimately the ones that like
we would like to have
the most accuracy on
accounting also for variance estimators
and so epsilon this big e has been
pulled out it's the set of all error
neurons
we then adapt the core predictive coding
dynamics equations from a hierarchy of
layers to arbitrary graphs
change
in v
the nodes
with respect to time
prediction is happening through a
sequence of observations in the
predictive coding architecture that's
that now casting column filter frame
differencing a lot of these other sort
of real-time
algorithms for mean and variance
estimation that we talked about
equals
the change in f
free energy
with respect to change in the note
so now the loss function through time
is going to be
related to the f
that had been previously
previously defined in in earlier
equations and then that is going to be
defined as basically the error
this is in formalism 30 the epsilon sub
i
so the the error variance at that
last level
minus
a sum
of c
so c are the children
and then there's just some more terms
involving basically tuning the nodes
accounting for the fact that we want to
like tune the variance estimators
and the compute
computation nodes that represent the
mean estimates
and so
then the dynamics of the parameters on
the vertices v
and the edge functions theta so they
kind of slightly evolve the edge
notation
towards
theta
can then be derived as a gradient
descent on f where f is the sum of
prediction errors of every node in the
graph
so
um they had specified how the the
composability of the multi-level
predictive coding architecture
is such that
the levels
are
can be factorized from each other
which allows us to sum their free energy
contributions into like a free energy
total
and so that is how a multi-level model
can be fit
because it's finding like the free
energy
minimum for that whole multi-level
system
which might entail one of the levels not
being at its like perfect perfect lowest
free energy state
and in this section
they've connected
the way that back propagation
in 28 and 29 without any action without
any prediction
is able to make a big loss function
that's composed because of the
tractability
of the compute graph
and all of these little loss functions
can be summed into a big loss function
that you use to like train a neural
network for example
um
and then
moving that into
the predictive coding and free energy
minimizing space
by saying well this is a special kind of
compute graph that has the mean
estimators mu and the variance
estimators the error terms
and then we're going to do
something similar
where we're going to compute like
what amounts to a loss function
f the sum of prediction errors of every
node in the graph
based upon the internal
prediction errors being minimized
so in the non-predictive coding
um frame
we're minimizing a big loss function
that's composed of smaller loss
functions in the predictive coding frame
we're minimizing our divergence from
expectations
composed of the divergences from many
smaller expectations
okay yeah go for it
of extrapolating hopefully again from
this
that the predictive coding then
like by
working with the errors
which are kind of almost
uh i know i'm making a little bit of a
jump here but um i kind of implicit to
the
to whatever the system of
uh interpretation is on the data
it is quite um it's kind of that's why
you're going into this biological world
because it's so bottom up in a way
um because it can start just with
um
whatever the errors are
in the nature of the um
the system that's been set up for doing
the sensing
even forgetting action just the nature
of how the sensing set up
will start to generate the errors
at some implicit level
would that be a fair assumption
so anytime there's going to be a
prediction of observations so yeah we
don't need action here yet
there's two options
either you have a 100 predictive power
and your error is zero or there was some
error
so you're always in one of those two
cases and which one are we usually in
not having the total perfect 100
accuracy down to the you know 100th
decimal point
if for no reason other than that's
beyond the point of of diminishing
returns or we're also trying to balance
accuracy
with model complexity
so because we have these metrics like
the aic the bic
all these metrics that find us a model
that's a balance between accuracy and
complexity
so it's not overfitting
the cost of not overfitting
of
cost of having a simpler model is
literally increased error because every
new parameter that you add into a model
you always explain more variance the
first principal component takes the most
variance of the data the second
principal component takes the next most
variance of the data every principal
component on a data set is going to
continue to eat more and more variants
out of the data leaving less and less in
the error term
but
it's a situational thing whether you
need to explain 80 of the data or 90 of
the data or 95 of the data but there's
always going to be some difference
between the
prediction and the observation again
unless one is in this super edge case
where it's perfectly known
so yeah go for it
yeah that's that's helpful and
it's also implicit there
that if even if you in whatever you set
that complexity and accuracy to at this
very deflated level
is is is really helpful so the nature of
the model
will change the nature of the errors
and basically the best it gets to
by the most it can reduce will vary a
little bit as you change that model
um and
not making too much of an extrapolation
but that that
is a nice way to be able to
unify a lot more complex and verified
ideas
about models and
you know what is really happening
um
you can sort of drop back to that
complexity accuracy
principle
so here's some more sections from 4.1
towards the end of 4.1 on page 30 in the
paper so yeah hopefully we've been
representing this at least mostly
accurately and then for those who want
to go deeper that's why there's a paper
and that's why there's like
a continued discussion and development
on these ideas because they they drop
many little crumbs
of well we've held this to be zero for
simplicity and
but they write
we can think of this as a predictive
coding network in which all the error is
initially focused at the output of the
network where the loss is and then
through dynamical minimization of
prediction errors at multiple levels
layers this error is slowly spread out
through the network in parallel until
the optimum distribution
the error at each vertex
is precisely the credit that should be
assigned to causing the error in the
first place
that's pretty interesting it's kind of
like let the chips fall where they may
with respect to error and variance
attribution
dean
this is this is awesome so
are they also are they also is the
way the architecture is and the way the
graph
the graph is set up as kind of a mirror
of
what the architecture is of this
layering thing
are they also there to kind of contain
little fires of
of mistakes
and errors is that why it's effective
because it sort of contains something
you know suddenly
causing a chain
reaction and having and having
everything
and when we read majeed's paper about i
think it was major maybe was axel's
paper about you can
you you could make
predictions going right off of a cliff
and and the result is you no longer
exist is this kind of an architecture
that
helps us avoid
some of those really
consequential prediction
consequences
that's an interesting idea
i think we should engage in some slide
play
and try to
try to get a little bit of clarity on
that and like also hopefully we'll hit
on
um
[Music]
a lot of the ideas that we've been
bringing up in a more abstract way
because i know it
it's helpful for like everyone to see
multiple
coats of paint on this and like it it's
the the epitome of abstraction
is the austerity of those
formalisms about compute graphs so let's
think about a um we won't take it to the
um the cafe
level
um that was even though that was i
remember that being quite fun um
we're gonna be we're gonna be between
the cafe
um
and uh you know
something else so we'll we'll be
intermediate because we're going to be
talking about a specific graph but we're
not going to like necessarily for the
first pass on it go all the way in okay
so
the
node that we care about being most
accurate on is seven
so like this is going to be like our our
focal note
this is like
the one that we want we want to have an
image classifier algorithm
this is the classifier node we want to
have um prediction on what the
thermometer is going to say that's what
this is we want to have prediction on
the temperature in the room that's what
this is we want to have
inference on action
and think about the upstream
parents
of action
then that's what this note is so seven
is going to be like the node that we're
interesting
uh interested in minimizing
our loss function on
okay
this can be carried out on multiple
variables but we're going to just look
at minimizing on this okay
what is the back propagation chain here
well let's think about what the forward
and the reverse arrows are so first just
to clarify like this is a directed
acyclic graph there's no loops in the
graph and the arrows are all directed
um
they reflect
differentiable functions causal
influences amongst these
uh variables these intermediate
computational
products so like variable one
is then there's some function
differentiable function
that translates it into two
two influences four and three
three influences five and six six
influences seven
okay
we've seen this in the bayesian context
where the sparsity of the connections
allow for the factorization
of this graph
like it allows us to sort of
hold one part
um unchanging and change other parts
through factorization that's a lot of
the variational inference stuff that
we've talked about okay so what are the
parents of seven
which nodes do you think that we should
consider if we're going to back
propagate so the forward model
the actual like causal chain in the
model not in the world
is like one you could imagine some
perturbation happens to one
every node is going to be influenced
that's the forward perturbation in the
forward generative model
what
is going to be invoked if we start at 7
and do a back propagation
which nodes are not important
five and four
right yeah five and four will not be
invoked
in this
optimization scheme
so if we were
so we'll make these ones gray that we're
going to be backpropagating on
but um and i i also hope i'm
representing this accurately
but um
you could imagine that like
changing the dials on 5 or the function
between 3 and 5
will not reduce
the loss on 7.
so it still might be an important thing
in the forward model
but it's not in the back propagation
from seven it's in the forward
propagation from one
um okay
so then
um this is not a predictive coding
architecture because in the predictive
coding architecture some of these
um
that's what we saw in like for example
in figure two
is what we saw in figure one
so
there's the means and
the
variance estimators so let's bring in
figure 1
and try to adapt it to our graph
so our graph is sort of
up to formalism 29.
now
we want to think about a graph that's
not just nodes and edges of the abstract
type
but it's going to be nodes and edges
that include these error neurons as
they're calling them here
okay so here's a reminder on what that
architecture
looked like
jax wrote how is the back propagation of
error related to
um
uh holland's john holland bucket brigade
the bucket brigade in signals and
boundaries it sounds explain a little
bit what is the bucket brigade or we'll
look but it sounds like a bunch of
people helping and
sharing buckets or something like that
um
okay
so
let's just say that the one that we
actually want to minimize is going to be
like a mew
it's going to be a mean estimator
now let's just modify this graph so that
this one's going to be error
i'll just use the um
won't
type the variables so this is a mean
estimator
and then we're going to alternate
so that this one
is an error
and this one is a mean
this one's a mean again
this is not the exact same architecture
that they laid out and this might not be
um traditional or um
classical standards but like this is
getting us towards this idea
that within a cortical column
so to speak
we have
um
the forward propagation of alternating
layers of means and errors
we want this
loss function to be minimized
by diffusing
the uncertainty across
these error nodes
that is like letting the chips lie
in terms of the variance attribution
and as they write precisely the credit
it should be assigned to cause the error
in the first place
so
if like
node two in the forward causal
model
was causing 90 of the variance
and so this was like like one
was you know is a very tight
distribution
and it gets blurred a ton on the way to
three
and then from three it only gets blurred
a little bit on the way to seven
so like two is going to be big
this is like a big error estimator
and six is small
tiny variance estimator
so it'd be like if we were in
classical statistics and we were going
to do
um you know we were doing
brain imaging
on
a bunch of people from two different
categories
like with and without this diagnosis
you could imagine that in that two-level
model one world there would be like
massive variance amongst people
and very little differences between
those two higher groups
in another world it could be the
opposite there could be big difference
between the two groups but very small
differences but amongst the people
within a group
and so
this is the parameterization and finding
the parameters that are going to
minimize the loss function
means that we want the variance
to be partitioned
appropriately
across error terms just like we would
like the average the mean estimators to
be accurate
the equivalent in the error world
is we want the errors to be appropriate
in how they're distributed
so it's like it's like if you're doing a
mean estimator
on something you don't just want like
the highest mean possible you want like
the most accurate mean possible
and the most accurate error possible
doesn't mean the lowest error possible
that would be the fallacy of well we're
estimating means well then let's just
make it bigger
so we're estimating errors not because
we want bigger errors or want smaller
errors that's the thumb on the scale
estimating errors accurately
entails
appropriately distributing the error
terms
on this graphical architecture
and then they're adding in one extra
point which is basically that the
dynamics of predictive coding are purely
local
requiring prediction errors from the
current vertex and the child that is
um
on the computational front
a win for tractability
and for the actual algorithm
because you don't need to have the whole
model loaded into ram for example
because you might only you know which
neighborhood of variables you're going
to engage
when you're doing a certain parameter
update and then on the biological side
it starts also leaning towards
plausibility
because
like
they even call it an error neuron well
neurons are signaling forward let's just
call that the direction that the action
potential travels
down the axon
but there's also
retrograde signaling at the synaptic
junction
so it's plausible at the multiple neuron
architecture level
or even at the two neuron
biological system level that there is
like even if there's a direction at
which signaling is
assumed or perceived to be
normatively happening
there's also a retrograde signaling
of multiple kinds we won't go into that
like complexity of retrograde synaptic
regulation
but
that at the circuit level and at even
the synapse level the idea that
signaling is happening both ways
is something that is
seen as the strength of the predictive
coding architecture again the locality
allows it to be more computationally
implementable
and this sort of bi-directionality and
signaling is more reminiscent of
biological signaling processes synapses
conversations brain regions so on
okay let's
okay yeah any thoughts on this
i think that that's a pretty good
explanation go for it stephen
just just checking so
if you added all the errors up
like are the errors kind of independent
of each other or would they
is there like a total error
across the
chain so to speak of like
uh how much error there can be
or is it like
kind of
contained within
the switch like is six relatively
contained
and two relatively contained
okay dean
can i take a guess stephen yeah sure i'm
get i'm guessing so just
keep the wild a money money part of this
front of mind um
i think what the
i think what the graph is telling us or
at least when we
formalize it in this way
is that
you could always
find the cumulative error but the point
of the system is to
try and keep the error
where it actually exists within each
layer so sort of sort of partnering the
error
at each level with with whatever the
prior or the hierarchical l plus one or
l minus one
layer is but me again
i'm just guessing but i'm kind of making
sure that i understand completely what
what daniel laid out here and that would
be my guess
i mean you could you can add it all up
but i think i think the point of it is
is that before it it runs away from you
this architecture is set up
so that
there will be some cumulative effect but
it probably wouldn't be
it
shouldn't be there's the word i'm
looking for it shouldn't be as
abrupt as if you didn't have the layers
and you didn't have the ability to
differentiate and you didn't have a kind
of understanding of what what is
happening i.e
back propagationally
now again i'm just throwing that out
there but because i don't have a
reputation around this i could be
completely wrong
there's a lot to say and the authors
like do
provide many citations but i i believe
that's right like
just as
appropriate mean determination we're
thinking in a gaussian world like
um
there's a lot to say on gaussian
processes but a gaussian
is a mean
and an uncertainty
so it's there's going to be somewhere
where the hump of that distribution is
and then there's going to be some width
to it
now
sometimes
the process is actually gaussian
other times we can use nested gaussian
processes
so that it's like well there's some
process that's moving it
and then there's wiggle around it so
we're gonna see that
moving as one galaxy and then the other
one is like a ripple that's like a
smaller gaussian on that
and then even in cases where there's a
non-gaussian distribution that's where
the laplace approximation comes into
play which is the second
derivative
we have the jacobian and then the
hessian matrix in 26
and then we talked about how when you
take the second derivative
you're basically making that bowl
and then lying in it
so you're going to the bottom of the
bowl that you created
and you know that it's going to be the
sort of
hump structure
that's amenable
to
going downhill
because once you go beyond quadratic
beyond the hump anything that's like a
multi-hump distribution or even just x
cubed
you're going to have challenges
getting globally optimal from local
optimization processes because you won't
know if you're in a local energy well or
not
and so
many of these computational tools and
approaches that we're discussing like
across these live streams and papers
can be understood
as taking something that isn't like a
bowl
and making it so that it can go downhill
and finding well what is the appropriate
level
of how many layers have to be added to
this onion or how many oven gloves do i
have to put on
how many approximations
should we carry out in our approximation
science
so that there can be something like
a parabola
where
we know that we're on parabola territory
and that's what allows us to then
minimize a loss function
because if one believed that they were
on a rugged landscape
then
minimizing something locally
would be you'd have no way to know if
that was on the right track or not
um yes stephen
and could i say then would i be okay to
say that it's almost like each of these
errors say number six number two
in here and you could have be like
little mini bowls or mini
um at different and the further up the
chain the bigger the potential
um
impact of the positioning in that bowl
or whatever the landscape is
out
towards whatever's being
you know the mean that's been understood
okay let's look at figure one
so this is a cortically inspired so
inspired by the cortex
and blue ro dean i understand the
architecture the same way error
correction is retained locally
so let's look at this
semi-cortically inspired
predictive coding
hierarchical
system
just like in the example with the two
clinical populations doing brain imaging
there's one world where the patients
within the group vary a lot and the
groups don't differ there's another
world where the groups differ a ton
and then the people within each group do
not have any variance amongst them so
depending on how it's parameterized
one could have a model where
the
um highest level
has a major influence or not
and that's the whole question it's like
in a linear model is it more important
like the um
mx part the slope or the b how much it
shifted
well
if the regime of attention is on linear
modeling as an architecture
it doesn't make sense
because they're both just parameters in
a model
now for any given data set it's an
empirical question to what extent
changes in the slope or the intercept
are associated with changes in the loss
function
and that's linear regression
here's an architecture
that gives us
an approach to finding loss functions
but how do we know how many layers
how do we know how many of these side
connections to make
but there's a few ways to go about that
one could just a priori
model the structure
of the model of the graph around
something else like previous work or
some inspiration from a biological
system
they might also be interested in this
structure
being a parameter of a model
like
and that's the whole
structure learning
and
meta-bayesian approaches and all of that
but that's pulling back another level
and so that's the
the challenge of structure learning
because we can get that loss function
within
a given static graph
but that doesn't mean that we have the
best possible graph architecture
it's like if you have 100 pieces of
data biometric data on people and you're
making a multiple linear regression to
find out their risk for some condition
do you just use 100
that might be overfitting it might be
too costly computationally so how many
of those variables do you use
there's a process for determining that
what's at the trade-off between
accuracy and complexity where it's
fitting
the outcome well
the loss function on the condition that
you're trying to actually predict
but it's not past the point of
diminishing return or using variables
that are uninformative or for example if
there's two variables that are perfectly
correlated with each other
um that's called multi-linearity and
like you wouldn't want to use those
variables
so
that's the challenge in the linear
regression world and this is like taking
it into another space but it has more
analogies than not which is why spm
statistical parametric mapping that
textbook is
um for those who want to engage
vital
prerequisite
because it addresses a lot of these
questions on model fitting
including on dynamical systems and it
puts it with
six feet on the ground
in classical parametric and
non-parametric statistics dean
this just
raises the question in my mind i haven't
answered it as to whether or not a mean
is constructed
or if a mean
is actually sculpted
or some combination of the two i mean
being a min 2 guy i'm going to assume
that it's probably
both
like you can have the figure
but it's your understanding of of
what the difference is between an edge
and a and a
and a directional link which you have to
kind of carve out from the overall image
but that's again that's one of these
things now where if you get into this
predictive coding piece
i think the product looks like a
construct
but an actual but in actuality there's
there's got to be a huge element of this
of
being able to isolate
the mistakes so that they don't
overwhelm and if you're isolating
something if you're removing
some factor you're actually sculpting as
well
so maybe that's a bit of a philosophical
overlay on the sort of mathematical
operational side
but you know me i'm always trying to
turn it into what's the what's the
practical
function of this
yeah it's like statistics
as world building because
if you just want the mean
then just
take the grand average if you want the
mean and the variance there's a method
do you want a variance on the variance
how confident are you that it's 10 plus
or minus 1
is it 10 plus or minus 1
plus or minus 0.5
or is it 10 plus or minus 1 plus or
minus 0.01 so a tight estimator
on the error as a parameter
and so we're like playing with which
parameters
are seen as like the things in and of
themself
the means
and which ones with respect to means
have this interpretation as being error
neurons or being variance descriptors
now
one
properly fit model which you could take
into the you know 50
stacked levels 10 plus or minus 1
and then on that one variance estimator
we have plus or minus 0.1 and then how
how sure are we about the plus or minus
0.1
0.01 okay now how sure are we about that
0.01 0.001 that would be like a well-fit
model where as we kept on adding
uncertainty parameters we would be
making appropriate
estimators
now what would be like a male fit model
and i hope this is accurate
10 plus or minus 1 and you go how sure
are you on that one
plus or minus 50.
it's like
the variance just exploded it's like
well but you're saying that the variance
could be like
zero
or the variance could be 50
how much confidence should we then have
in the mean estimator
and so that's what this appropriate
distribution
of uncertainty is now let's think about
node
seven an uninformative node seven
we're predicting temperature but it's
just it's unchanging
we don't have a lot of information there
to fit a world model
because it could just be a single level
estimate it's 10 and it's not changing
but as we deal with progressively more
and more
nuanced and informative things that we
want to minimize loss functions on like
natural language
images from natural scenes
action including the unknown
consequences of real-time unfolding
action
those
because the uncertainty
becomes higher
and the information content of what
you're trying to minimize your loss
function on is higher
it
um
not authorizes or licenses but kind of
moves us into potentially having higher
levels of model complexity
as simple as possible and not simpler
with that principle being carried
through
again if you're just trying to predict a
constant number you don't need a six
level predictive coding architecture
whereas if there was something that did
actually have
that many levels
of depth
that's the kind of architecture that
would do well to predict it and we
talked about this with the um par and
pazulo
on the architectures for homeostasis and
allostasis
and it was like yeah to just recognize
if you're out of bounds and then come
back in
that's a given model
but then there's a different graph
that's going to do something like
intermodal or anticipatory or have
memory so all of those cognitive or
computational features
license or engender
more complex causal models but these are
being sculpted
ab initio from nothing by the
statistician
and then we're in sort of brackish or
gray waters
when
we um
[Music]
juxtapose
the architecture of the graph
with the architecture of
some natural system
okay yes
stephen
yeah and you've got this and you've got
this excitary and inhibitory
dynamic going on
um and even though the arrows going from
the error down to the
the u
the there is a the the u is exciting the
layer above isn't it it's exciting so
it's almost like
it's like one bottom up is kind of
exciting
higher up areas and then
things that are further up also sort of
saying hey calm down calm down i can
reduce some of this
you're getting a bit out of hand here
you know they've only scored two goals
let's relax you know
that that
again i also hope this is not uh
inaccurate
it's almost like um there's a
suppression of error like a dampening
being carried forward
with the ultimate dampening being
you predict it perfectly
you have totally quelled all error
yet in real settings
because of just simply model
simplification or uncertainty in the
world
error is coming in
from the observables which is often what
we're trying to reduce our loss function
on and that's this whole difference
between
reinforcement learning finding oneself
in reinforcing or rewarding states and
active inference with reducing surprise
about outcomes
we're dampening error and carrying that
forward in the full regenerative model
and then also able to run it back in a
tractable way
because it's like
you're you're you're dampening the
vibration but then the vibration is
still entering in and you'd want that
vibration to be appropriately
distributed according to where it should
be okay dean and then stephen
yeah
it seems to me that the way
what this is what this is saying to me
is that
because of the way things are organized
um
two two things can live
simultaneously at once one is sort of
that
local
mean
correction and the others the more
generalized global
or
the other direction in the
bi-directionality parallel
of
of mean correction one is kind of
reinforced through
external evidence while the other one is
localized
almost almost
it is distributed but it's almost like
the ability to localize and isolate
if necessary so i know we've talked a
lot about top down and bottom up but
this brings a lot more
color in my mind
to some of those conversations we've had
before in terms of
you know arrows going in opposite
directions and it's not so much that
they're going in opposite directions but
that you can be going
two different directions quite literally
we want literally at once because of the
way things are set up
so yeah i think this this has been
really really helpful for me in terms of
not only understanding what back
propagand propagation is but actually in
sort of giving me a little bit more
foundational
ideas around again how do we turn this
to these sort of statistical
ways of representing it into
so i'm confused should i
should i go into the cafe or not i mean
we do not not all of us have to go to
that level of detail to really
understand what the final thing was that
pushed us
over the door threshold or not but it
appears that
it's this has been around for a while
and
being able to take that
if you really are kind of
stuck
because you really don't know
what the the parents are of your
current
action because we haven't got as you say
we haven't got to action yet but that's
the whole point there is an architecture
there that's going to
allow us to have choice
thanks um this minimum of two
um
comes up so
much so it's awesome to hear about that
and then to connect like expectation
maximization
and the tale of two densities
epistemic and pragmatic it's like
wherever we look there's partitions into
two
into multiplicity and unity through
plurality
and then other times even within the one
road
there's the movement in both directions
forward and backwards in time
or the forward propagation of a
generative model
which could from just one if all you
knew was one
you could simulate sevens
if all you knew was seven and the
structure of the network of course
you could back propagate
the best possible mean and error
estimates using
back propagation of error okay stephen
this is helpful for thinking about how
we perceive things as well for
that was dean was saying about making
choices it can be when we get zero error
or whatever seen as negligible error you
want to just allow that to carry on and
stay with your imagination so i go to
the bar
and i
a lot of things are the same right maybe
there's a happy hour sign and if that's
unusual maybe i'm happy about that i
note it
um
but if a lot of things are exactly or
very similar to how i expected
then in a way my perception is probably
mostly
my predictions
just not being
contradicted it's all they all actually
i just don't see it i just i think i've
seen it but i just don't need to see it
and where there's something which is
like ambiguous like you were saying you
need that number seven we're going to
use this diagram starts to have to be
looked at you know you start peering at
things straining their eyes
trying to sort of see well what's that
is it is it a dog is it a man running
into the woods is it a dog is it a man
running into the woods
um
you you know you start to notice
things so i think this is also quite
useful for that perspective of
you know when when you just you don't
actually need to see a lot of stuff it's
quite an efficient model right if it's
if if the area goes below a certain
level you just move on and carry on of
course that's where the challenge with
autism is they think because
too many things have been looked at that
are possibly negligibly
relevant at the time
okay thank you okay so just one last one
last thing before because i know you
want to
kind of clean this up
i think then one of the analogies that i
draw is
with the emphasis on the word minimum
two min two doesn't mean
it's always a you know a hard
bifurcation and a or a binary
it means that
the minimum amount of things like even
when you
take your shoelace and wind it through
all the eyes of your shoe you've got two
ends
that you eventually will loop back
together and and entangle in some way to
hold your shoe on so even though it's
one lace
i think what a lot i think what active
inference
reinforces because it's got active and
inference is that ability to be able to
see two things
both seemingly contradictory and both
actually true now it can be multiple
things you can have
multiple
as as you can have multiple surprises
some of which are make you quite happy
and others where
you walked in and said well why hasn't
it been happy hour at this hour when
i've been at the if this far on multiple
other days like you could be
disappointed in that
as well as being
pleasantly surprised so i think
what this again i just reinforced is the
the minimum
of two allows for the integration the
minimum of two recognizes the
differentiation and when we're talking
about
statistical issues and when we're
talking about errors
and when we're talking about
energy um i think
i think the way that they that these
folks have been able to discover what so
what architecture would allow for that
is what's really interesting to me now
because i i wasn't even thinking in
these sort of
so what's what is the
what does the scaffold look like
but it looks like there's been a lot of
work done in this area so
so
let's take it to action as we head into
our last little bit on this and of
course if anyone is more author or not
familiar with the formalisms just
contribute to acting flab help us
annotate the papers
and read these deeply because there's so
much to learn and somebody getting
involved like a few days or weeks
before these streams
is a leverage point if you want to help
other people understand this area
so
i've changed the colors just all to gray
because they're all just random
variables now
we had the seven so we were back
propagating error on temperature
prediction
but also maybe this system is predicting
um pressure
and so then three might be like
estimating
you know
is the water boiling
again just we're getting one one step
closer to the cafe
so if if we were only trying to predict
temperature we would back propagate
along the seven six three two one route
if we were only predicting pressure we
could back propagate along eight five
three two one
the fact that there's a parent
that is upstream
it's like the last common ancestor of
pressure and temperature
like we might be able to reduce um
these errors a lot on the temperatures
by having this higher order variable is
the water boiling and so we can imagine
like if the answer is yes then it's like
it's expecting that this is like higher
on both and if it's low it's lower on
both
so the generative model can go from the
water's boiling what pressure and
temperatures do i expect and you can add
a third node
it allows you to
condition on a cognitive structure
go from observations of just temperature
around the horn
to pressure
or from pressure and temperature
up to the water boiling but the
influence of these observations
is like limited
through this choke point
it's actually a markov blanket with
respect to what's on the either side of
it
let's bring action into the picture
action can also be understood as
parametric
what angle should my elbow be at
what angle should the eyes
be
oriented
those types of things again not whether
that's what the actual neural signaling
in the brain is doing but this is how we
model action it's like the the car how
many miles per hour should i be going
those kinds of questions
is parametric modeling of action
and that's what was so fun and exciting
was the first 50 equations in this paper
have scaffolded this tremendous general
node computation architecture
multi-level
means and variances forward and backward
up down left right
all of these interesting ways and
connections
but not yet action not because we hadn't
brought action in as a dancing partner
but actually this was above
any interpretation of the nodes as
inference or action
and then
it's as easy to condition on action
as it is to condition on any other
inference
because action is just a parameter
for parametric active entities that are
engaging in
action as inference planning as
inference and so on
and so then one can think about what is
the compute graph
whether it's composed of just nodes and
edges
or whether we think of some of those
nodes as being like variance estimators
and then um you know this
uh maybe again the connections i'm not
gonna rewire this whole graph
but just like
is
is this a water boiling
situation
okay
so we have a thermometer it says that
it's 100c
it's boiling temp we did the the
pressure sensor is broken
but we back propagate it
we're in a water we're high confidence
on the water boiling
then
this is like another variable that's
going to require like a different sort
of question that it's answering
but one can imagine
that if this is a water boiling
situation
and the water is not boiling
there might be an error
and so
how can we reduce loss function
on the total compute graph including
observation and action
how can we reduce uncertainty
about a cognitive model including
observation and action
there's two ways to do it
and it's how they introduce it in the
very um beginning of the
of the paper
which is that
um the minimization
of the loss function
of the free energy
expected free energy variational free
energy can be achieved in multiple ways
through immediate inference about the
hidden states the world
explaining perception
updating a global world model to make
better predictions
slower parametric inference updates that
have the interpretation of learning
and
when action is a variable that we have
agency over
it introduces some complexities like the
need to have preference and the need to
specify a time horizon and to have
uncertainty about the consequences of
action right wouldn't it be easy if we
were just watching the movie and our
actions didn't have any influence upon
the story that we saw it'd be a
different inference
and finally through action
to sample sensory data from the world
that conforms to the predictions
potentially providing this integrated
account of adaptive behavior and control
so it took us 50 equations
at the general before we could jump into
action
but it's a deflationary approach to
because action is a parameter
in a broader cognitive and computational
framework okay stephen
thanks daniel yeah that's really helpful
actually going back to that the example
with water as well
you can even bring in the higher level
of um
affect in the sense that one thing
that's really hard with water compared
with a lot of other things when you heat
up oil on stuff is you can have the
water boiling you probably had it and
and you could have a thermometer
theoretically saying 100 but the steam
can go above 100 but it's very hard to
really
it can trick you right it's like it's
hard to it's actually quite hard to get
i find it hard to get my head around
steam being hotter than water because
it's kind of
just kind of how i know
you just think of it as being 100
degrees water right and it's almost like
if you were to get into that situation
or after i burnt myself one time or
there's almost maybe i i just start to
have a feeling of fear
if i have a sense that i'm somewhere
where
what might be coming out is high
temperature steam right
um even though and that will override
the fact that perceptually
i haven't got a lot of ways to
easily
sort of
gauge that visually unlike say a ring
getting red
and you know
other
things okay
here's here's what that makes you think
of
sometimes
we
have
indirect cues
that reduce our uncertainty about
something that's not directly observed
like the mood ring if everybody was
wearing a mood ring
and that was an accurate
predictor
you know that would be this other
alternate world
and so there are certain kinds of
variables
that are more like the magical mood ring
or like the temperature of metal within
a range because i mean
it's only going to start to get glowing
when it's super super hot
so it doesn't help you differentiate
whether it's free like at 0 c or 50 c or
200 c probably even but there's some
range
for certain things in the world
where we can use
indirect sensory cues
um
affect is not
quite here
in this model in this graph
but we've talked a lot about how
uncertainty
can be understood as like anxiety and or
negative valence
in the world of reward maximization
less reward is bad in the reward
um in the world of precision
optimization
excess
variance is bad not any variance
it's not a simple
you know destroy the variance estimators
it's about the appropriate applications
of variance
but excess variance more variability
than expected you told me it was 10 plus
or minus 1.
but i just pulled 3
negative 80.
that's confusing it's more confusing
than i thought
so then some of these mean
and error estimators
in
a computational model might have
this could be a mean estimator on
valence
or one could choose to
write a paper
where an error estimator
is framed as being an anxiety parameter
and that's always that that that um jump
between what any parameter is in a
graphical model
and anything
about the world or attaching it to some
word
because oh it's anxiety well then that
makes me think of this other situation
but so you can send someone really
too easily down
a road of associations
when the deflationary perspective is
just stating what it is
um
okay fun didn't didn't expect that we
would go this way with the back prop but
blue mentioned it last time and and it
is important to uh
bring up and also
it connects
to modern
methods for training
neural network architectures and that's
what a lot of the authors research has
focused on so let's just continue to
explore action a little bit
they reiterate
that
when we're thinking about
active inference about inference
involving action so cybernetics control
theory
any area where some parameters represent
observations or latent states
and other parameters represent active
things
the first way that you can minimize
prediction error
is to update predictions to match
sensory data corresponding to perception
and the second is to take action and
earlier from the introduction of the
paper they kind of
did a little minimum of two even on this
which is to split out perception
as rapid inference
and learning as a slower updating but
we've talked about the continuity
between perception and learning like if
you're seeing the ball move across the
screen
is that perceiving the movement of the
ball
or
is it learning a parameter representing
the location of the ball
so
the whether we call something more
perceptual
or more learning oriented and and even
abstract learning can be seen as like
perception in interior spaces which has
been the focus of a lot of work by
fields 11
with
competency in navigating these abstract
spaces but perception sometimes brings
us a little bit um
not too close but a little bit um
just linguistically to like our
experience of perception
when the phenomenology and the qualia is
not what is in play here it's about
parameter updating in the model yeah
dean
do you think daniel it's about sample
size but sample size is related to
maybe the
the time commitment
like if i'm inferring something that's a
very very
short
volume
of sample
versus prediction which is
slightly or relatively
larger volume
of time commitment to move to that
volume and then modeling for example
which which
takes the the perception and tries to
um build some something material from
that
is that
do you think that that
counts here because at least that's what
i was
that's what i was telling participants
we had to take under consideration was
sort of the time factor of the sample
sample
sampling process
sure
i think um
if we allow inference
to um be just broad and including
everything then that's what it is but
yeah just in its connotation inference
using a model
often has the um
it's sort of like the machine is ready
the model is ready and we're gonna do
inference the new patient comes in with
a biometric data we're to do inference
using this model and we're going to
predict their risk of the diagnosis
that's the fast perceptual time frame
learning
is unless it's one-shot learning
is taking in multiple patients and
updating the parameters of those models
now those two stages can be alternated
like an expectation maximization
or in the tail of two densities
but that doesn't get away from the fact
that there's sort of this like one data
point mode
like plug and chug inference perception
mode
variational free energy
and then there's a little bit more of
like the updating the model parameters
it's like are you tuning the engine or
are you using the engine
loosely
in the um
non-action space
in this first
way to minimize prediction error those
given the ongoing stream of patients
coming to your office
there's two ways to reduce your surprise
those are the um
perceptual and learning
continuum
which does come down to the specifics
about like the sample size like you're
in the architecture of learning and
perception
um you could also reduce surprise
by
choosing what to sample
and or modifying the world
so that's how they bring action in
and
it's very
interesting to think how many
um pages of pros
i've gone into
wondering where action fits in and
there's still many more pages to go
in terms of
where does
formalism 51 take us
have we
um cached the check
of pragmatism and activism
extended cognition
and so on like what is 51
with respect to all the qualitative
insights
of action
with all of its depth
where what is 51
a short answer might be that it's like
the y equals mx plus b
with respect to all the ways that linear
models are used in the world this is
just like a sort of skeleton
archetype
that is just the trace
or a hint
for someone who then wants to analyze
specific actions over specific time
frames for specific cognitive
computational models but
that's where 51 takes us steven
yeah one other
piece that could be kind of interesting
to throw in there as well as
matching my uh the sensory data with my
predictions
i could re-imagine
my
reality
to explain
my beliefs
which in a way would mean i create my
own sensory data
by proxy if that makes sense which is a
kind of an interesting
slight
add-on to that but um
it's the same idea because you're not
strictly
taking action you're taking actions
to match sensory data but not
necessarily the real world sensory data
it could be the
the kind of
uh you know the imagined world data
i i am seeing an angel coming over the
top of
that hill now you know
yeah one could engage in um mental
revery
and it would either be reducing their
surprise
in the long run
or
that system would fail to persist in an
entropic world
and people have made
all kinds of arguments like in
evolutionary psychology
about the basis of why we perceive or
believe different things along similar
arguments
so definitely makes sense let's just
look a little bit
in 452 which we didn't um previously get
to but of course anyone with any other
like questions in the live chat welcome
do so
so
here
um in 26 live stream 26 we talked about
pid control we talked about integrator
chains
and about generalized coordinates of
motion
so just
um
a reminder on what 26 looked like
we had
from left to right is time these are
different time points
and then at each time point there's this
vector is like a stack
reflecting the observables
and then also
things
that are um latent states they're not
observables of the world
real or imagined
they're
the derivatives of how the observables
are changing
and those can be the position
it's like the zeroth derivative but then
also velocity jerk so on acceleration so
on
so
we looked at that in 26 but it wasn't
connected
formally to predictive processing
predictive coding
um
pid control
is restated in 53
using the formalisms
um
using the notation
that is going to prepare for the merge
with predictive coding like a for action
epsilon for errors
um
[Music]
and so the the
error term
is included in all of the three levels
to obtain the equivalence to predictive
coding
we utilize a linear identity generative
model with three levels of dynamical
orders so the joint distribution of all
the o's all the observables and all the
x's
through time
is going to be this factorized
expression
so the distribution of the observation
conditioned on the latent state
and then that
is
conditionally independent of so it
allows it to be factorized and
calculated out separately here's like
the first derivatives
second derivatives
with o double prime and x double prime
here is
x
conditioned upon its own derivative
the derivative of x conditioned on its
derivative
and
the um
sort of root node is the double
derivative of
x
because this one like stands alone
that's like where our model kind of taps
out that's equivalent to
node one here
like
there's no variance term leading to one
there could be but then that would be
a different model
so these equations in 54
restate
this dynamical model
and introduce
omega
which i believe would be an error term
this w
and also the muse which is the desired
set point for x at that order so at the
first second or third
um derivative what what is desired there
um
then that allows
so so this this is like a graph where
instead of these being different things
like what if what if
kind of mixing architectures a little
bit
because the generalized coordinates
doesn't have errors interleaving
it just has
the
state the first derivative the second
derivative and so on
rather than interleaving error terms but
we can imagine another similar graph
where as you back propagate
it's like higher and higher derivatives
that's the integrator chain
but
i guess in 55
56 and 57 and 58 they do something
similar
to what we had done with the generic
computation graph
or to the predictive coding architecture
with the interleaving of the means and
the errors
this is just that
on the graph architecture
where the nodes have this interpretation
of being derivatives
of one another
what is there to say that's an
interesting production
this is bringing back flashbacks to try
to
try to get my head around
500 level economics courses and when
you'd have somebody walk in and start
pounding stuff up on a
whiteboard on and you know second third
and fourth derivatives and just
just feeling like you'd been tossed into
a blender and you had no way of avoiding
the blades
so i'm glad i'm glad that there's people
that can do this stuff
but i would have to dedicate way more
time to trying to parse what the heck
they're talking about because
it i it's a wall to me
it's really hard
so yeah i i i feel you maybe for the
last few minutes we can kind of pull
back to
okay
as we
swoop out of this bathtub out of the dot
too
into the great beyond like
what have we taken with us why was this
lengthy journey through predictive
coding and the 60 formalisms and
what maria brought with the thousands of
years of philosophy and history on
perception so
where are we
and how are we different
now and going forward
than we were before we started 43.
well i'll i'll say what it what it's
done for me
first of all bringing up the historical
piece of it was really really helpful
because
this didn't just sort of come up
yesterday or in the last couple of years
it's been around for a while
i think
for me predictive i wouldn't have seen
predictive coding as a as a
sort of formalized way of retracing a
navigational route but that's what it
screamed to me in it and after the point
one i um
listen to you having hearing you and
blue talk about it
when the when the idea that when the
question around back propagation came up
that's when i sort of did a deeper dive
on that
and again it wasn't
i wasn't picking up on how to do that
path retracement the formalisms weren't
really addressing what i thought was
being said i think what today helped me
with is
sort of examining if you if you don't
have traces laid down
that are material that you can see if
you weren't actively part of the
building of the path
that there is still
some
graphical
statistical ways
of
organizing information to give you a
better sense of
okay so you didn't lay the breadcrumbs
down
but we can still give you a better sense
of where you came from
as a result of being able to use this
kind of
formalism
i mean i honestly daniel 53
53 come on
i mean if you
if you're one of the people that was
able to write those 53 out and actually
present it in in paper form i mean props
to you you get you get many
thank yous but
holy mackerel other than the fact that
that there is some evidence now that you
can retrace even though you don't have
necessarily those
markers or
you didn't self-correct you didn't you
weren't aware of how you self-corrected
whereas the predictive coding at least
gives you an opportunity to maybe trace
that retrace that back
even though you didn't spend a lot of
time trying to
organize the evidence the other thing
that it does is i think it reinforces
the idea that the way
that these live streams are structured
which is just introduce the paper just
give the paper its
its opening like open up the box
in the point two
you can actually go into one particular
area of the unknown which for me was the
back propagation which
you and
steven help me with
in the point two
we are still doing the part where
the point 2
could always even if you didn't have a
record of the point 1 and the dot 0
this paper told me that you would still
have some way of knowing
where that
elusive.
exists relative to this
this live stream today and again i could
be over i could be overfitting but i
don't think i am
otherwise why would you why would you
string out 53 operations
a lot of interesting stuff there so so
um
because this is level this is the exact
same i mean what we're doing in the live
stream and the levels that they're
talking about
they they affect each other in exactly
the same way it's diagrammed out here as
a stack and we tend to think of ours
because it's over
multiple
multiple days as sort of a horizontal
continuation
but they're essentially one and the same
oh that's that's very interesting um
so it's almost like
well there's
the dot zero and the one of the two they
can go both ways so in in the temporal
sense
the dot zero is a precursor temporally
it's the dot one the dot two so for the
for the um
for the uh youtube channel subscriber
this is their observation oh
43.0 oh 43.1 has been live streamed 43.2
has been live streamed
but
um what is like the derivative that sort
of sets the initial conditions for dot
two
it's the dot one
yeah
and then what of course sets for the dot
one dot zero
and so there's almost this sense in
which as we
um
[Music]
dampen our uncertainty through action
and inference moving forward
in a world that's always continually
vibrating and transcending our model
like
it pushes the earlier actions that we
take that high school teacher
that book that you read
all the way back even beyond one's own
corporal birth
as like
parameters that
dampen or specify if one doesn't want to
think about dampening
the position acceleration and velocity
and so on
um they're like higher and higher chains
and that means that they have like
they're further and further away from
where the rubber hits the road for the
youtube subscriber on the outside
but they're absolutely like part of the
process by which something comes to be
and then the dot two you said can exist
without the dot one and then then
the first time it made me think of like
the negative numbers
like even before the zero what is what
is there before zero what
happens before
zero is there a negative number
there's no number that's positive that's
smaller
but
what is is it is it a letter
is it a shape
like
is it its own big bang it's like and
there's a sense in it that it is and
there's a sense that it isn't
um
that's it
part of it's the pre-reading the other
thing that i think
maybe doesn't sort of register
explicitly is that
the error propagation in the way that we
do the live streams remains
there are some corrections and there are
some
there is a sort of a gradual movement
towards a bit of minimization
but every time we
we
come together and try to figure out
we don't come from a position of we
figured it out
we come from a position of well what
will we what will we do with this today
so
we retain that error propagation
and i think that that's a
i mean
that's not convention convention is why
would we spend time on something where
we leave
a bunch of error
baked in
but i think when when again if we're if
we're going to differentiate if we're
going to truly integrate if we're going
to be able to say that you can have a
0.2
existing with a without a 0.1 and a
point zero of course you can but how
superficial is that relative to
the method
because of the architecture because of
the way it's structured how much deeper
you can actually go
and how many times you can
bump into a dead end immediately find
out how quickly you're going or you know
going off the rails so to speak because
i can't remember which one of the live
streams was that you had the
the train moving down the track but you
can find out whether or not something is
a dead end quickly
and re-correct that's what that
retracing part today
i think is one of the
well it's it's the takeaway from this
this set of live streams that and i
wouldn't have anticipated based on the
title of the paper
that that retracement piece
was going to be the thing that was going
to sort of
percolate
and and make the most sense in terms of
why
the structure is is
yes there's an optimizing piece to it
but there's also a piece that
that allows for mistakes
without without
you know
i mean sometimes it's very consequential
but lots of times
it's the consequence is what's minimized
not the error
and i think that's what the architecture
affords you want to talk about
affordances
so when you said the consequence is
minimized and not the error that makes
me think about like high reliability
organizations
of course
one way to minimize the consequences of
error would be to never have errors
zero tolerance
for anything
but that is challenged in a world again
that's always throwing us um
challenges
so
in in um
in that setting it's almost like the
observation
here the one that we actually want to
reduce our loss function on
is not the um so-called proxy of error
occurring
but we could reduce our loss function on
function
on the thing working and just say we're
minimizing the consequences of all this
upstream stuff some stuff that might
have the interpretation of error and
things that might not
they're just nodes in this graph
and then what is going to dampen
surprise about the consequences
and so like if you say you know anything
that you say to me right now
uh
i'm going to accept it
and believe it
and then it's like in a in a trust space
that opens up
there to be
like
a communication
that goes deep
if it's being honestly said
and that's because like what's being
minimized like it don't tell me
something surprising
it's like
my consequence
you can have precision on my consequence
that's one direction of the conversation
and that is what allows that second
direction to really come into play
with the transmission of
variability
and rather than
well how am i going to reduce my
uncertainty about action relative to
what the person is going to tell me
i won't talk to them
or i'll tell them what to tell me
or um
i'll leave them in the dark about how
i'm going to act
and then they'll have uncertainty about
how i'll act if they say something even
trivial
and so i think this like really
it
spans many levels and ways here because
there's nested levels and deep chains
but i i agree i think on the more
topical
um
if such a thing could exist some of the
the takeaways that that i had also um
really um appreciated maria providing a
lot of the philosophical context and
then that one part where we're like
wasn't this a meme like thousands of
years ago and in many cultures in the
world what is it
that still makes
the predictive mind
and surfing uncertainty and being you
what makes these
novel and surprising
and even somehow counter-cultural
what what is happening there what chain
is leading to that
where the idea that we're generators
with agency
rather than passive receivers why is
that
such a hill to climb and die on that's
one piece i
absolutely take away
then
it was awesome with blue um
to work on this in the dot one
where we had like on the bottom left the
qualitative philosophical insights
and and
connecting to
technical and formal insights on the
bottom right
and biological systems and it's sort of
like
where are we engaging deeply with one of
these vertices
where are we engaging deeply with an
edge
where are we trying to grab two vertices
and the edge or
go around the horn or where are we
trying to really go for the triple play
um
every baseball
at home base
inference in action
um
[Music]
in the bottom of the ninth of the dot
two
it's it's a full count and it's a power
play
that and then also i think the last
piece that i kind of take away is just
when the
computational and cognitive framework
are defined generally enough
like at the level of a graphical network
which opens up message passing
variational inference
back propagation of error predictive
processing architectures
hybrids of all of these approaches
then
action
is deflated
or it's inflated maybe or whatever it is
that we even say it becomes composable
and tractable
to discuss
open-ended combinations of
perception cognition and action and
impact which is the home base in the
niche and so
if even that model has to be
structurally revised
like we end up having another
way of framing entity and the niche
interaction
it may fit within this framework or it
may necessitate revision of the
framework but within the entity niche
interaction space and the nested systems
and the counter factual cognitive
systems
there's almost
like less and less to action
than it seems
it doesn't remove the challenge of
action
it
it reduces something else that i'm not
quite sure about what it is
like it doesn't make it easy
but
something is being removed as we're
learning and working through this
but it doesn't make the climb
well it makes the climb different to
think differently
but it doesn't move doesn't mean that
fewer foot-pounds of force have to be
applied
but there is something different about
the navigation
around action and inference
via active inference
that i think is will continue to develop
for a long time
yeah okay dean and also stephen
thanks a lot
wasn't sure there for a second at the
beginning what would you gotta think but
i gotta thank you again daniel because
obviously you did understand have it
we'll have a reasonable understanding
far more than mine in terms of what that
back propagation implication was in
terms of marrying it to the predictive
coding so
didn't mean to put you into the tudor's
seat today but appreciate the fact that
you're able to
sort of pull it apart and then
put it back together in a way that made
a lot more sense than just reading it
off the page so
thank you sir thank you dean
see you later all right take care
bye
you